Guide to the Weinstein Family papers, 1912-2012 MS 857
Woodson Research Center, Rice University, Houston, Texas
Weinstein Family papers
1912-2012
Woodson Research Center, Rice University, Houston, Texas https://library.rice.edu/woodson
Weinstein, Riki
MS 857
.50 Linear Feet 1 box
The Weinstein Family papers showcase Irving and Lily Weinstein, and their ties to the broader Houston Jewish community. Irving's service in World War II and Lily's civic engagement with both San Jacinto High School and Congregation Beth Israel are preserved in the letters they exchanged while Irving was overseas. Featuring photographs, news clippings, and a plethora of military correspondence and documentation, the Weinstein Family papers offer insight into a century of Jewish History.
Biographical / Historical
Irving Weinstein was born in Galveston, Texas on March 8, 1912, and moved to Houston with his family in 1929. Irving graduated from Ball High School, the University of Oklahoma, and the University of Texas Dental School. In 1940, he married Lily Chernikowski Weinstein, his wife of 72 years. During World War II, Irving served as a member of the 8th Engineers, First Cavalry Division. He participated in landings on the Admiralty Islands, and was later sent to Brisbane, Australia where he directed and supervised the dental clinic of the 383rd Medical Dispensary. In 1946, he returned to his general dentistry practice in Houston and practiced for another 50 years. A longtime member of Congregation Beth Israel, Irving was also a life member of the Texas Dental Association, the Harris County Dental Society, Masonic Lodge Temple No.4, Scottish Rite and Arabia Shrine.
Lily Chernikowski Weinstein was born in Zurich, Switzerland, on Dec. 18, 1917, and moved with her family to Houston in 1923. She married Irving in 1940, and volunteered her time in numerous civic, educational, and charitable organizations during World War II. A life member of the Texas State Dental Auxiliary, the City of Hope, and the San Jacinto High School Alumni Association, Lily was also a member of congregation Beth Israel. Irving and Lily had two children, Jay and Riki Weinstein.
Scope and Contents
The Weinstein Family papers contain photographs, news clippings, books, and documents relating to the Weinstein family, and Irving and Lily Weinstein in particular. Irving's years serving in World War II are well-documented by both his membership cards and official correspondence, and the letters that he wrote regularly to Lily during his time overseas. Lily's attendance at San Jacinto High School can be explored through her yearbook from 1934 and reunion programs from 1974 and 1984. The materials (excepting the San Jacinto High school yearbook, which is fragile) are in good condition, and range in date from 1912 to 2012. Researchers interested in Jews serving in World War II, Jewish education, or the Houston Jewish community would find this collection helpful.
Conditions Governing Access
This material is open for research.
Stored offsite at the Library Service Center and require 24-hour notice for retrieval. Please contact the Woodson Research Center at 713-348-2586 or woodson@rice.edu for more information.
Immediate Source of Acquisition
The materials were donated by Riki Weinstein in February of 2019.
Arrangement
The materials are arranged by date in a single general series.
Index Terms
Subjects
Jews and Jewish life; Newspapers--Sections, columns, etc.; Soldiers--Correspondence; Military
Document Types
photographs; invitations; letters (correspondence); personal correspondence; marriage licenses; certificates; yearbooks; membership cards; programs (documents); books
Subjects (Persons)
Weinstein, Riki
- Series I: General Series
  - Baby's Childhood Biography, 1912-03-18 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Event Invites & Information, 1916-1987 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Marriage and Citizenship Certificates, 1917-1939 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Family Photographs & Portraits, ca. 1927, n.d. (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Newsclippings, 1932-2012 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - San Jacinto High School Yearbook "El Oroso" [Fragile], 1934 (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Correspondence with Army, 1940-2001 (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Letters exchanged between Irving Weinstein and his wife, March 8, 1941 - December 12, 1942 and December 18, 1944 - January 13, 1945 (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - Abridged Prayer Book for Jews in the Armed Forces, 1943 (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - Military Documents, 1943-1946 (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - 1st Anniversary edition of Pilam Inquirer & Reporter (Pi Lamda Phi), 1945-06-07 (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - San Jacinto High School Reunion Programs, 1978 & 1984 (Box 1, Folder 12)